<?xml version="1.0"?>
<!DOCTYPE PubmedArticleSet PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD PubMedArticle, 1st January 2018//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pubmed/out/pubmed_180101.dtd">
<PubmedArticleSet>

<PubmedArticle>
    <MedlineCitation Status="Publisher" Owner="NLM">
        <PMID Version="1">29524752</PMID>
        <DateRevised>
            <Year>2018</Year>
            <Month>03</Month>
            <Day>10</Day>
        </DateRevised>
        <Article PubModel="Print-Electronic">
            <Journal>
                <ISSN IssnType="Electronic">1573-2517</ISSN>
                <JournalIssue CitedMedium="Internet">
                    <Volume>234</Volume>
                    <PubDate>
                        <Year>2018</Year>
                        <Month>Mar</Month>
                        <Day>06</Day>
                    </PubDate>
                </JournalIssue>
                <Title>Journal of affective disorders</Title>
                <ISOAbbreviation>J Affect Disord</ISOAbbreviation>
            </Journal>
            <ArticleTitle>Correlates of sedentary behavior in 2,375 people with depression from 6 low- and middle-income countries.</ArticleTitle>
            <Pagination>
                <MedlinePgn>97-104</MedlinePgn>
            </Pagination>
            <ELocationID EIdType="pii" ValidYN="Y">S0165-0327(17)31996-1</ELocationID>
            <ELocationID EIdType="doi" ValidYN="Y">10.1016/j.jad.2018.02.088</ELocationID>
            <Abstract>
                <AbstractText Label="OBJECTIVE" NlmCategory="OBJECTIVE">Sedentary behaviour (SB) is harmful for health and well-being and may be associated with depression. However, little is known about the correlates of SB in people with depression. Thus, we investigated SB correlates among community-dwelling adults with depression in six low- and middle-income countries.</AbstractText>
                <AbstractText Label="METHODS" NlmCategory="METHODS">Cross-sectional data from the World Health Organization's Study on Global Ageing and Adult Health were analyzed. The analysis was restricted to those with DSM-IV Depression or receiving depression treatment in the last 12 months. Self-reported time spent sedentary per day was the outcome. High SB was defined as ≥8 hours of SB per day. The correlates (sociodemographic and health-related) of SB were estimated by multivariable linear and logistic regression analyses.</AbstractText>
                <AbstractText Label="RESULTS" NlmCategory="RESULTS">In 2375 individuals with depression (mean age=48.0 years; 60.7% female), the prevalence of high SB was 11.1% (95%CI=8.2%-14.9%), while the mean (±SD) time spent sedentary was 215 (±192) minutes per day. Socio-demographic factors significantly associated with high SB were older age and being unmarried, being male and being unemployed. In other domains, no alcohol consumption, current smoking, mild cognitive impairment, bodily pain, arthritis, stroke, disability, and lower levels of social cohesion, COPD, visual impairment, and poor self-rated health was associated with greater time spent sedentary.</AbstractText>
                <AbstractText Label="CONCLUSION" NlmCategory="CONCLUSIONS">Our data suggest that future interventions seeking to reduce SB among individuals with depression may target at risk groups based on identified sociodemographic correlates while the promotion of social cohesion may have the potential to increase the efficacy of future public health initiatives. From a clinical perspective, bodily pain and somatic co-morbidities need to be taken into account.</AbstractText>
                <CopyrightInformation>Copyright © 2018 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.</CopyrightInformation>
            </Abstract>
            <AuthorList CompleteYN="Y">
                <Author ValidYN="Y">
                    <LastName>Vancampfort</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Davy</ForeName>
                    <Initials>D</Initials>
                    <AffiliationInfo>
                        <Affiliation>KU Leuven Department of Rehabilitation Sciences, Tervuursevest 101, 3001 Leuven, Belgium; KU Leuven, University Psychiatric Center KU Leuven, Leuvensesteenweg 517, 3070 Kortenberg, Belgium. Electronic address: davy.vancampfort@kuleuven.be.</Affiliation>
                    </AffiliationInfo>
                </Author>
                <Author ValidYN="Y">
                    <LastName>Stubbs</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Brendon</ForeName>
                    <Initials>B</Initials>
                    <AffiliationInfo>
                        <Affiliation>Physiotherapy Department, South London and Maudsley NHS Foundation Trust, Denmark Hill, London SE5 8AZ, United Kingdom; Health Service and Population Research Department, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology and Neuroscience, King's College London, De Crespigny Park, London, Box SE5 8AF, United Kingdom; Faculty of Health, Social Care and Education, Anglia Ruskin University, Chelmsford, United Kingdom.</Affiliation>
                    </AffiliationInfo>
                </Author>
                <Author ValidYN="Y">
                    <LastName>Mugisha</LastName>
                    <ForeName>James</ForeName>
                    <Initials>J</Initials>
                    <AffiliationInfo>
                        <Affiliation>Butabika National Referral Mental Hospital, Kampala, Uganda; Kyambogo University, Kampala, Uganda.</Affiliation>
                    </AffiliationInfo>
                </Author>
                <Author ValidYN="Y">
                    <LastName>Firth</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Joseph</ForeName>
                    <Initials>J</Initials>
                    <AffiliationInfo>
                        <Affiliation>NICM, School of Science and Health, University of Western Sydney, Australia; Division of Psychology and Mental Health, Faculty of Biology, Medicine and Health, University of Manchester, United Kingdom.</Affiliation>
                    </AffiliationInfo>
                </Author>
                <Author ValidYN="Y">
                    <LastName>Schuch</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Felipe B</ForeName>
                    <Initials>FB</Initials>
                    <AffiliationInfo>
                        <Affiliation>Universidade La Salle (Unilasalle), Canoas, Brazil; Escola de Educação Física, Fisioterapia e Dança, Porto Alegre, Brazil; Department of Psychiatry, Universidade Federal do Rio Grande do Sul / Hospital de Clínicas de Porto Alegre, Porto Alegre, Brazil.</Affiliation>
                    </AffiliationInfo>
                </Author>
                <Author ValidYN="Y">
                    <LastName>Koyanagi</LastName>
                    <ForeName>Ai</ForeName>
                    <Initials>A</Initials>
                    <AffiliationInfo>
                        <Affiliation>Instituto de Salud Carlos III, Centro de Investigación Biomédica en Red de Salud Mental, CIBERSAM, Monforte de Lemos 3-5 Pabellón 11, Madrid 28029, Spain; Research and Development Unit, Parc Sanitari Sant Joan de Déu, Universitat de Barcelona, Fundació Sant Joan de Déu, Dr. Antoni Pujadas, 42, Sant Boi de Llobregat, Barcelona 0883, Spain.</Affiliation>
                    </AffiliationInfo>
                </Author>
            </AuthorList>
            <Language>eng</Language>
            <PublicationTypeList>
                <PublicationType UI="D016428">Journal Article</PublicationType>
            </PublicationTypeList>
            <ArticleDate DateType="Electronic">
                <Year>2018</Year>
                <Month>03</Month>
                <Day>06</Day>
            </ArticleDate>
        </Article>
        <MedlineJournalInfo>
            <Country>Netherlands</Country>
            <MedlineTA>J Affect Disord</MedlineTA>
            <NlmUniqueID>7906073</NlmUniqueID>
            <ISSNLinking>0165-0327</ISSNLinking>
        </MedlineJournalInfo>
        <KeywordList Owner="NOTNLM">
            <Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">depression</Keyword>
            <Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sedentary</Keyword>
            <Keyword MajorTopicYN="N">sitting</Keyword>
        </KeywordList>
    </MedlineCitation>
    <PubmedData>
        <History>
            <PubMedPubDate PubStatus="received">
                <Year>2017</Year>
                <Month>09</Month>
                <Day>25</Day>
            </PubMedPubDate>
            <PubMedPubDate PubStatus="revised">
                <Year>2018</Year>
                <Month>01</Month>
                <Day>10</Day>
            </PubMedPubDate>
            <PubMedPubDate PubStatus="accepted">
                <Year>2018</Year>
                <Month>02</Month>
                <Day>25</Day>
            </PubMedPubDate>
            <PubMedPubDate PubStatus="entrez">
                <Year>2018</Year>
                <Month>3</Month>
                <Day>11</Day>
                <Hour>6</Hour>
                <Minute>0</Minute>
            </PubMedPubDate>
            <PubMedPubDate PubStatus="pubmed">
                <Year>2018</Year>
                <Month>3</Month>
                <Day>11</Day>
                <Hour>6</Hour>
                <Minute>0</Minute>
            </PubMedPubDate>
            <PubMedPubDate PubStatus="medline">
                <Year>2018</Year>
                <Month>3</Month>
                <Day>11</Day>
                <Hour>6</Hour>
                <Minute>0</Minute>
            </PubMedPubDate>
        </History>
        <PublicationStatus>aheadofprint</PublicationStatus>
        <ArticleIdList>
            <ArticleId IdType="pubmed">29524752</ArticleId>
            <ArticleId IdType="pii">S0165-0327(17)31996-1</ArticleId>
            <ArticleId IdType="doi">10.1016/j.jad.2018.02.088</ArticleId>
        </ArticleIdList>
    </PubmedData>
</PubmedArticle>

</PubmedArticleSet>
